welcome back to 25-minute Fizz today
we're talking about exercise programming
in other words putting the other workout
programs we talked in the 5-minute fifth
section about the seven modifiable
variables so in other words you're
deciding to write a new workout program
for yourself or for a client what are
the things that I can change that would
alter the adaptation or the result that
I get out of my plan so those seven
modifiable variables and we'll talk
about those in separate videos but in
this particular talk we want to focus on
that first modifiable variable which is
exercise choice other words known as
exercise selection so how do I pick the
right exercise well if we took our basic
template right and we decided to work
our new workout program and if you sat
down on your computer and you open up
Microsoft Excel or Word or whatever you
use and you sat down and it looks
something like this and you said okay my
new workout program I'm so excited I'm
gonna get jacked up or lose a bunch of
weight or whatever I want okay what am I
gonna do day one okay let's see well I
know let's see squats are important so
maybe I'll squat okay then I guess maybe
do some more squats and then I'll just
pay a trainer
all right or I'll get a program online
well that's usually what it looks like
and what this hat what happens or what
causes this is poor planning or a lack
of planning so what I want to do in this
video is talk about those 11 things that
you can use to help decide the exercise
choice now if you come back and follow
up with the 55 minute video I'm gonna go
into detail about how to actually do
this what big things to consider and how
to pick your specific exercises but for
this example I'm just gonna give you
some things to consider I'm gonna walk
you through those explanations a little
bit about what they mean and how they
can might alter your exercise choices so
I know sometimes when you're writing
these workout programs or if you've ever
paid one got one from a coach or from a
trainer you feel like it's this magical
sorcery or there's this magical book
somewhere they're consulting and all
this
they should you pay them and they go
away for two weeks and also they show
back up with this perfect recipe and
every single thing is dialed well it
doesn't have to be that complicated I'm
hoping in this video we can demystify
that a little bit so you understand the
rationale that most good coaches are
using or maybe lack thereof all right so
what I did is I put together an avatar
and I just totally made someone up and
we'll call this person Randi so I want
to walk you through how I would actually
consider what I would consider with our
person Randi here and how we would put
together his program or how we would
select his exercises so let's say we
have a sample day here where we've
decided for whatever reason on six
different exercises overhead squat
deadlift rows glute bridges etc well
what we need to understand is I talked a
little bit about this in the five minute
for this episode is what separates a
coach that doesn't know what they're
doing but still might make the right
decision from a coach that really
understands everything is if they can
walk through every single one of these
exercises and defend and justify exactly
why they picked and that exercise and
more specifically why they picked that
exact of variation so if we look through
on number one exercise number one and we
said okay it looks like I have
programmed to do overhead squats today
we should have a rationale that said
something maybe like this and I'm
literally just making this up as I'm
going
maybe we wanted to get some light leg
work in we want to also work the
shoulders in the back position okay we
wanted to also not worry about going
extremely heavy or not worried about
going to maximal fatigue because we're
gonna do those on a separate work out
well overhead squat is great for all
those things because you can't overhead
squat that much physical weight so
although it's a heavy for you relative
to the movement it's not very heavy to
your legs so maybe I pick an overhead
squat on a day that I know hey actually
the next workout coming is a heavy leg
squat day so I don't want to I want to
do a little legs today but I don't want
to crush my legs I'm more worried about
maybe developing posture or shoulder
position or doing a complex coordinated
movement now we could go through this
with ever
one of the six exercises but we don't
want to write will go through actually
that in more detail again if your coach
can't answer in that detail or better
they might make the right choices but
they really don't understand what
they're doing and you should ask it's
not disrespectful that question them
know you got to pay attention to your
tone but it's actually a good a good
advice for an intern if you're interning
or if you are a coach or an athlete to
ask hey coach I noticed that we're doing
overhead squats today I'm just wondering
why are we doing with the dumbbell is
opposed to barbells or why are we doing
it in this stance as opposed to this
stance I'm trying to learn right I
really like or I'm excited about this
stuff I'm trying to help understand if
you use that tone you're usually gonna
get a better response if the coach knows
what they're doing they're gonna give
you some really good insight if they
don't I'll give you some insight as well
well we're really trying to get at here
is answering one very basic question
which is why specifically did I make
that exercise selection with all of the
variables to come with us so why did we
do this version of the squat or this
version of the ab exercise or why did we
grab this implement versus this
implement a kettlebell versus a dumbbell
why are we using AB and here why are we
doing this one on one leg coach versus
two-legged why are we doing this with a
partner or why am i holding my knee in
this position as a weight as opposed to
that position because every single
variation you make alters a little bit
of the exercise if we look at these two
exercises again over here on this side
of the screen as you're normal that
overhead squat position with your
classic barbell and over here is
actually just a modified overhead squat
so in this particular case I'm using a
kettlebell I'm only doing it one arm I'm
doing it also on one leg and I'm
standing on a goofy medicine ball and if
you're wondering yes I did complete that
all the way down and back up well it's
not that one of these is better than the
other one in fact if you have a coach
that says that or if you are currently
saying that shame on you
right there are no such things as good
or bad exercises there are no exercises
that are better or worse than others it
all depends on the exact situation all
we have is exercise
is exercises give us good things and
exercises don't do some things we need
to understand all those idiosyncrasies
so that we can understand our selection
a little bit better so and in the case
of the right over here
the the one-armed on the medicine ball
thing that would be a better exercise
selection than the barbell version if I
was trying to work on say unilateral
stability all right so this is stability
on my right arm and my right leg I'm not
gonna get that on the with the other
picture because by doing that
bilaterally meaning two arms and two
legs at the same time I can use my other
side to fix any deficiencies I have on
one side so if I did this exercise over
here the one arm one leg thing and I was
able to do five repetitions and good
with good technique with fifty pounds
and then I went to my left side did the
exact same exercise on the other side
and I could only do 30 pounds for three
repetitions I would immediately identify
I've got some sort of asymmetry between
my science alright so that would be one
of the benefits of doing the overhead
squat in this fashion now a downside
could be how much weight can I possibly
load do you think that's going to
sufficiently tax the strength of my
glutes or my hamstrings probably not in
fact I it might be simply so complex
that the technique of it limits all
productivity or most of the productivity
especially in terms of strength right so
again every exercise has a strength and
it has a weakness we need to be able to
identify that and consider every aspect
when we're making our exercise selection
so let's jump into these things a little
bit more detail now last time I gave you
the overview of the 11 things I said you
should consider this is not everything
you should ever consider but I think
this is a very good starting ground so
let's dive into these I'll go through
them and give you some specific examples
number one what's the goal of the sport
or the activity you really need to
understand your clients desires or the
the reason you're putting the current
program together that will help you make
your exercise selection so if I am
programming in this example for our
fictional character Randy and Randy is
interested in
the sport of weightlifting or Olympic
weightlifting well the barbell overhead
squad is probably the normal or the
better exercise choice because that's
more specific to that person's goal or
sport or activity if I'm interested in
simply becoming more well-rounded or
more athletic or I'm want to just have
some fun in the gym or maybe I'm
interested in gymnastics or maybe I'm a
practitioner of parkour maybe in that
case the one foot one arm medicine ball
squat is more related to the goal of the
sport of activity but let's consider
that first another thing to consider
your proper energy systems now you'll
have to go back and watch some different
videos to understand what those things
are but does the exercise allow me to
train in the proper energy system ok so
if we took our one foot one-armed
squatting example how many repetitions
can I possibly do probably not very many
and I probably can't do it that that
heavy unless I'm exceptionally talented
which for the record I'm not alright in
that exercise so if I was trying to pick
an exercise and I was trying to work my
lactate system or I was trying to get
some severe conditioning in or maybe
even aerobic endurance steady-state
conditioning something like that that
would probably be a very poor exercise
choice because the technical limitations
don't allow me a train of the proper
energy system right now if I were to do
something again like I wanted to work my
lactate system or work anaerobic any
anaerobic energy system
well the overhead barbell squats
probably a little bit better because it
allows me to train in that system where
I can actually feel confident where I
can push the conditioning and push the
pace while not feeling like I'm I'm
nervous and physically scared that I'm
gonna get hurt so I'm focusing more on
that than I am getting tired so I
reserve and hold myself back ok so does
the exercise selection allow me to go as
hard as I need to go or as easy as I
need to go depending on the exact energy
system we're trying to work into number
three sport specific now I will
certainly have a different video for
this term because it is horribly
misunderstood it does not mean it has to
look like your sport all this simply
means
is well the skill reasonably transfer
over to the sport or the activity or the
competition the person is doing alright
again just because it looks more or less
like it doesn't mean it's more sports
specific so for example a common
misunderstanding here is take the sport
or activity of running well you may know
that running is almost always one foot
at a time so in other words you never
have to feet on the ground at the same
time with running people use that to
then say all of your training should be
done on one leg in other words you
should never do this exercise over here
because you'll never be on two legs when
you run well that's probably pretty
short-sighted and a fundamental
misunderstanding of exercise physiology
and strengthening auditioning really but
nonetheless it is true your exercises
need to have some specificity towards a
sport you're you're competing in number
four muscles involved now we'll talk
later the separate talks about the
difference between programming by muscle
split so in other words I do my biceps
today and my triceps tomorrow and and
things like that versus whole body
movements but we do need to consider
what muscles are involved what muscle is
probably the primary mover what muscles
is the tertiary or secondary movers or
the core share your or later down the
road what am I trying to use what should
I be using what did I use yesterday what
am I going to be using tomorrow so that
I don't overuse a muscle unless that's
the goal right so we want to consider
that we on that also help us pay
attention to things like overall balance
so I may not realize oh my gosh I have
just done five exercises this week that
are actually PEC major and I haven't
done anything for PEC minor and matter
of fact I haven't done anything for my
posterior shoulder rotator cuff mmm I'm
kind of grinding the wheel only on one
side I'm not necessarily balancing it on
the other so paying attention to the
muscles involved a quick example let's
say we want to do some sort of pull-up
okay we know we want to do some sort of
pull-up but do I do the overhand grip or
do I do the chin up supine grip well
that changes considerably specifically
when you rotate move your hands this way
I now tend to use my bicep a lot more
I need to consider that if I know that
tomorrow is a heavy bicep day or
tomorrow's a heavy deadlift day which
the deadlift also contended especially
if you have a supinated grip and the
deadlift can tend to put a lot of strain
on the bicep don't believe me there's
been plenty of strong men have torn
their biceps in half during a deadlift
so we need to consider all those things
involved even though the pull-up is
traditionally a back exercise depending
on the variation I'm using how wide my
grip is where my stance is that can use
or turn off different muscles so we want
to pay attention to the entire packs
your entire picture or tire package of
not only the exercise as a general
statement but very specifically the
exact type or form or method I'm using
to get the exercise and how that's gonna
affect the muscles involved number five
you should also probably consider the
injury status of the individual so I may
have a great plan to do some one-armed
kettlebell swings today and the athlete
shows up and says ah man my wrist is
killing me
okay well if I understand what I was
trying to get out of that one-arm
dumbbell swing I can now modify the
exercise to accommodate the injury but
still get the primary adaptation so for
example if I was using that exercise as
a method to let's say simply work the
back that's all I cared about is I
wanted to work the glutes in the low
back well maybe I can now move to a
dumbbell or barbell deadlift and I'll
actually give the athletes some straps
so I take some pressure off the wrist
because I wasn't really concerned about
training the grip or the forearm that
day conversely if if the purpose of my
one arm kettlebell swing was to get some
a little bit of glute stuff done but
also get some unilateral stability of my
anti lateral flexion or a lot of
reflection well then I needed to come up
with a way to do that without actually
harming the wrist so I'll have to modify
my exercise choice right now I work a
lot with combat sport athletes and have
in the past and this is I can tell you
something that is every single day
you're gonna have to modify that if you
don't understand exactly what you were
trying to get out of your exercise
selection you have no prayer when you
have to make
on the fly decision to change or alter
the exercise you don't know what you
were shooting for so when you have
obstacles show up in the way you'd have
no idea how to modify things you're
simply guessing it won't take long
actually honestly - for your athletes to
figure that out and then sort of go back
to the beginning with our magical
potions then sort of like you're just
pulling stuff out of a hat you don't
really understand what you're doing here
but I promise you if an out they can
show up to you and you say hey look
we're doing split foot a 1/4 foot in
front of the other all contralateral
bicep curls and they go oh man I can't
because my left elbow is killing me and
you can immediately go oh ok you know
what the purpose of the exercise is
actually just to work on some stability
so you know what we'll do the same exact
exercise well I won't have you do the
curl or maybe I'll have you go to an
overhead press now I'm still working my
stability cool I understood what I was
programming the exercise for so I can
make an alteration and that athlete will
go oh cool and I'll actually say well
well isn't that a bicep movement is that
that no that's fine coach that's fine
athlete that's not we didn't care about
the biceps today we were actually doing
it to work on this and so we'll go to
here and they'll go oh ok so we awesome
I don't have total confidence in you so
being able to work around your injury
status number six the movement plane
right so am i working in the frontal
sagittal transverse plane where am i
working at am I trying to work
multi-plane am i trying to work
connection - connection so am I trying
to work rotational - vertical what am I
trying to do so making sure again this
is sort of similar to point number four
where we probably want to make sure that
we have at least somewhat of a
reasonable balance between the exercises
we select so that we have an equal
training in all of our movement plans
now if you're somebody who's simply
interested in bodybuilding maybe you
don't worry about six so much you're
probably more worried about the muscles
but if you're looking for general
conditioning for health for to generally
feel better for weight loss if you make
sure you have at least a reasonable
balance between all of your movement
plans and probably a lot of movements
that combine multiple planes what that's
going to do is allow you to train a lot
more often before you develop some sort
of imbalance
or before you get some sort of overuse
injury alright so paying attention the
movement planes when you're selecting
exercise is really important as well
number seven anthropometrics is this
kind of a fancy way of saying your own
body segment lengths so me for example
I've got a torso about this long right
my femurs not too big it's very very
easy my back tends to be longer like
that it's very easy for me to squat
however training partners of mine friend
of mine Doug Larson for a long time he's
kind of the exact opposite of me and so
I tend to be very good at squatting and
terrible at dead lifting and he is great
at pulling and not as good as squatting
because he's got a longer femur he's way
back his angles are better so maybe we
make a different exercise selections
based on our anthropometrics i've used
to work with Division one basketball
players I had a seven footer we had to
make some modifications that's a long
waist for him to go up and down when
he's doing overhead squats now we still
did snatch full barbell snaps from the
ground all the way down but if we really
wanted him to work and do a lot of reps
we had to modify some things later
because we didn't want him to get into
bad positions alright so again just
because you're tall doesn't mean you
can't do an exercise or short people
should always squat this way you know
I've heard people say things like hey if
you're tall you should always sumo squat
and if you're short you should always
conventional well I don't believe in any
of that I do believe though you should
consider it it's just not a situation
where it's always or never oh you're
over 511 you automatically go do this
you're under 510 you automatically go do
that it's not that simple but it is
something you should consider moving on
to number eight and that's exec sir size
progression so in other words are you
experienced versus a novice are you say
a freshman in high school versus a
senior in high school or a freshman in
college versus a senior in college
what's your training history look like
so you may need to and this is probably
the one that you're going to be engaged
with the most but you're probably going
to have to alter the exercise choices
you do based on their experience level
so for example if we take out a load or
two pictures again a novice or an
inexperienced lifter might be able to
pull up
off an overhead squat even though it is
a pretty technically difficult movement
that person is very unlikely to be able
to do the one arm one foot on a medicine
ball in fact you may have to go even
further back and you might have to go
something even easier than an overhead
squat and maybe something like just a
basic bodyweight squat right so you need
to modify the exercise selection
depending on their experience their
abilities and what they know how to do
what they can't do so for example they
may be very very experienced in
squatting but they're very unexperienced
in body weight movements so even though
they've been training for 10 years or
they're an elite level athletes they may
be inexperienced in some other types of
movements so you may have to regress
them back to their abilities within that
movement category number 9 now as we're
getting towards the end their mobility
of flexibility of course we want to have
everyone going through full ranges of
motions at all their joints but we
understand that mobility flexibility
range of motion however you want to call
it can be different so we don't we want
to make sure we're not exposing athletes
or non athletes to too much ability or
too much exercise too much movement in
an unsafe environment for them that
doesn't mean we can't ever get them into
a little bit of a bad position we want
to be cognizant and careful of that and
so we may all turn exercise so for
example if we're doing overhead squat
and somebody just can't get into good
positions we're not going to force them
all the way into that overhead squat and
have them doing a bunch of exercises
there because we love the overhead squat
because it works well for me right I
need to pay attention at none it's not
about me it's about you or my client
right whenever you're writing these
programs for your athletes pay attention
to what it is for them not for you just
because you like that exercise it
doesn't matter you're not the one that's
important here you're not the star of
the show so make sure we modify things
based on their own mobility and
flexibility until we can improve it
number 10 the need for variation now
I'll do this one all the time I'll do
what I call my hotel workout so a lot of
times I'm traveling and you guys you've
done this before where you'll go to a
hotel you'll get want to get a workout
in so you go down to the hotel gym it's
like usually packed away in a basement
somewhere and you kind of walk in you
slide
your keycard and you open up the door
and you're like okay what am I about to
step into and it is a crapshoot for what
you get right so sometimes I will simply
do this we're all saying all right I'm
gonna walk into the hotel gym my eyes
are closed I'm going to do a set of ten
of every single exercise even piece of
equipment they have in that gym I'm
gonna go in a big circle whatever order
those things are in and I'm gonna do
three rounds of that getting slightly
heavier every single round until I can't
move and I'll end up doing like seven
different bicep exercises and two
triceps and six different crunches and
leg extensions and all these things now
those are exercises especially like that
one it's a great example a machine leg
extension that's something that is very
very very rarely on my exercise
selection list but sometimes I do it
because you know what I have the need
for variation it feels fun I can focus
on some different things and you know
every once in a while every couple of
months it's important to change up your
exercise selection so sometimes I will
change up those things if only for the
mental break or the excitement of
variation we used to do this in college
I play college football and one day a
year usually towards the end of the
season we're in playoff season it's been
seven I was probably more like 10 11 12
13 weeks of training I played in Oregon
so it was cold and rainy out you're
tired you're beat up you don't really
want to be there anymore and usually
when the morale would just get to the
very bottom of the team the coaches
would say okay it's reversi practice and
everyone would get so excited what that
meant is the offense played defense all
day and the defense played offense all
day so I was a defensive back so when we
got the one-on-one drills I got to be
the wide receiver and I got to burn
those crappy receivers that are trying
to guard me play defense on me when I
catch balls we got to throw the passes
as a quarterback we got to run the plays
on offense right now this is a pretty
high level in college we we were very
very good in college but it was simply
once a year we needed the mental break
we needed some variation we did a bunch
of movements we weren't used to right
because we spent seven or eight months
doing the same footwork drills every day
this
that 80% of practice was the exact same
so sometimes the need for variation in
and of itself is enough to change your
exercise selection okay our last one
here is simply ideal versus realistic I
kind of mentioned some similar things
with point number five injury status but
you're always gonna walk into your
program when you have your athletes or
your clients and you have an idea of
what's the most ideal what's the best
case scenario exercise choice but then
you often have to find face reality
so I mentioned working with combat sport
athletes tonight ideally I would love
for them to do full barbell snatches
from the ground all the way down to the
bottom realistically there in the Hertz
port they get kicked punched twisted
joints manipulated in the wrong way
every day it's just not very realistic
because the best part about Olympic
weightlifting or the best part about
like a dumbbell snatches or a barbell
snatch is almost every muscle and every
joining your body is working the
downfall of that is every muscle in
almost every joint has to work so if
anything hurts you really can't do it so
be very careful of this sometimes
especially for younger coaches are
younger trainers this is really hard
because you know what works really good
for you you're 25 years old or 23 years
old you're probably pretty fitting
pretty strong
nothing really hurts everything feels
fine and you're working with your
clients and you're like man why can't
you do this you know we should only have
to deadlift squat bench and maybe do
some pull-ups and you should be fine it
just may not be realistic for a 45 year
old man who's never worked out or hasn't
trained since he was in high school it
might not be realistic
for 12 year old girl right so you have
to take your abilities
move them out and determine you know
what this would be ideal I would love to
be able to do this but here's what's
realistic we might have to do some bicep
curls yeah that's a good example so I
used to train NFL players getting ready
for the NFL Combine where we eventually
had to have our Saturdays we turned in
to gun show days so this would mean they
would show up Saturday and we would pick
out like three like hey you you and you
you picked your favorite bicep curl
exercise you pick yours and then you
pick yours and I knew you and you you
pick your favorite tries try try and
then it'll be like
what's up and the first person to pick
it and be like I'd like to do this one
and we need to do as many reps as they
can to that one then the next guy would
go and they say as many reps is that one
the next one that was not any legit
at all with exercise selection but what
we were doing is that was the day that
they would come in and we will work on
the physical therapy we would do
recovery modalities stretching mobility
stuff what we found out is they weren't
showing up for those things so when we
gave them those bicep curls and those
tricep days they showed up that was like
a 15 minute thing we smoked their biceps
and triceps but then we got 45 minutes
or an hour in of the important work we
needed to do so ideally we would not
have selected the biceps or the triceps
at all but realistically it's something
we had to do or overcome to get what we
needed to get to okay so that's exercise
selection and I wanted to make you
mention of a couple of things though as
we're going in another video what I'm
gonna do is give you what I call my top
10 mistakes people make with their
exercise selection so stay tuned for
that I'll also throw up a 55-minute fizz
and go check out the 5 minute fizz if
you haven't done that you got any
questions let me know social media at
dr. Andy Galpin are on the website Andy
galloping calm thanks for tuning in
thanks for help me spread the word and
we'll see you next time
you